ALEJANDRO PARGA BECERRA MD PhD

Department of Neurology, University of Washington Veterans Affairs Puget Sound Health Care System 1660 S. Columbian Way Bldg 1 #615, Seattle WA 98108 parga@uw.edu (480)244-5947

Career Objective

As a neuro-electrophysiologist with medical training and advanced research skills in laboratory methods and computational analysis, I am an expert on the synaptic plasticity of neuronal circuits and their alterations in functional brain disorders. In my research, I bring together microscopy and electrophysiological tools to investigate perception. My strengths are in the interpretation of neuro-anatomical studies and the cell biology involved in neuronal circuits. My goal is to decode the neuronal informational flow that creates the mind and translate this knowledge into concrete applications that potentiate brain-computer interface technology.

Education

12/2014

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) Neuroscience

Barrow Neurological Institute - Arizona State University

Dissertation: Cortical auditory functional activation by cortico-striato-thalamo-cortico circuits: An endogenous mechanism of the brain to activate the auditory cortex, relevant to the neuronal basis of auditory hallucinations.

Committee: Co-chair: Co-chair: Janet Neisewander, Neuroscience. Ronald Hammer, Neuroscience & Pharmacology. Amelia Gallitano-Mendel, Psychiatry. Jim McLoone, Psychiatry. Jie Wu, Electrophysiology.

06/2005 **Doctor of Medicine (M.D.) Neurophysiology**

National University of Colombia – College of Medicine, Bogotá Colombia Emphasis: Developmental Neurophysiology

Academic Appointments

Senior Fellow

05/2017 – Present Dr. Christopher B. Ransom, Epilepsy Center of Excellence and Neurology Service, VA Puget Sound Department of Neurology, University of Washington, Seattle

• Regulation of Extra-synaptic GABA-A Receptors in Health and Disease

Postdoctoral Research Associate

01/2015 – 12/2016 Dr. Trent Anderson, Department of Basic Medical Sciences University of Arizona, College of Medicine, Phoenix

- Neurosteroid action on Cortical Spreading Depression (CSD) through differential Gabaergic signal onto pyramidal neurons
- Optogenetic regulation of CSD using targeted pyramidal inhibition and activation.
- Effects of CSD in intracranial pressure (ICP) as a model of migraine headache.

Research Experience

Research Associate

02/2008 – 11/2014 Dr. Ronald Hammer, Neuroscience and Pharmacology

University of Arizona, College of Medicine, Phoenix,

- Retrograded trans-synaptical tracing of auditory neuronal circuits using pseudorabies virus-152.
- Dopamine-induced auditory cortical activation and attenuation by D2-like receptor-selective antagonist in the caudatoputamen of the rat

04/2013 – 07/2013 Dr. Federico Sanabria, Department of Psychology

Arizona State University, Tempe

• Correlation between dopamine-induced auditory activation and sound perception during sound discrimination task

08/2009 – 12/2009 Dr. Athina Markou, Department of Psychiatry

University of California, San Diego

 Phencyclidine and clozapine effects on the 5-choice serial reaction time task and regional brain zif268 mRNA expression

03/2010 – 06/2010 Dr. Amelia Gallitano-Mendel, Department of Basic Medical Sciences

The University of Arizona, College of Medicine, Phoenix

• Detection 5-HT 2A receptor messenger RNA using *in situ* hybridization histochemistry on brains from EGR3 recombinant mice.

01/2000 – 12/2000 Dr. Jairo Zuluaga. Physiology Department

National University of Colombia

• Motor development and Epilepsy rotation. Neurodevelopment program. Central league against epilepsy.

Bilingual Interviewer, Group Leader

08/2007 – 12/2007 Dr. Mark Roosa, Department of Psychology

Arizona State University, Tempe

• Interviewed Mexican-American families and their children for The Family Project collecting socioeconomic data.

Teaching Experience

Teaching Associate

School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University, Tempe

01/2013 - 05/2013. Human Physiology and Anatomy Laboratory (BIO202)

- Taught human anatomy and dissecting techniques on human cadaver preparations
- Held laboratory sessions using a systemic perspective to assist students integrate anatomical and physiological concepts about the human body
- Developed students' learning skills via one-on-one interaction, using hypothesis testing through laboratory activities, and kept online support for the class

08/2008 - 12/2012. Animal Physiology Laboratory (BIO361)

- Implemented surgical procedures and paradigms for animal preparation in laboratory experimentations to expose the physiology of the nervous, circulatory, renal, and respiratory systems
- Provided training to students of the Assistant Teaching Associate Program for the development of their teaching skills. Created and managed online support for this training program.
- Taught physiological concepts for the classification of pathological disorders

06/2012-07/2012. Animal Physiology Lecture (BIO360)

• Developed and taught the Neurophysiology component of the lecture; held study sessions to answer students' questions

06/2010-07/2010. General Biology I (BIO201)

• Taught the scientific method and basic concepts of evolution in the biological sciences

06/2009-07/2009. General Biology II (BIO202)

- Taught fundamentals for scientific writing, proper citation formats, and online databases search used in reports, assignments, and the scientific literature
- Encouraged critical thinking through the analysis of the data obtained in laboratory sessions

Training and Mentorship

2011 A. Maple Graduate student DNA ribonucleotide probe radio-labeling 2011 J. Huang Graduate student ANOVA and regression analysis	2016	Z. Killeen	Medical Student	Live slice work for optogenetics
2012R. BastleGraduate studentDNA oligonucleotide probe radio-labeling2011A. MapleGraduate studentDNA ribonucleotide probe radio-labeling2011J. HuangGraduate studentANOVA and regression analysis2010M. LacagninaUndergraduate studentStereotaxic intracranial surgeries in roder	2015	J. Nichols	Graduate student	Post-Hoc Testing
2011 A. Maple Graduate student DNA ribonucleotide probe radio-labeling 2011 J. Huang Graduate student ANOVA and regression analysis 2010 M. Lacagnina Undergraduate student Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in roder	2013	A. Hoffman	Graduate student	In-situ hybridization histochemistiry
2011 J. Huang Graduate student ANOVA and regression analysis 2010 M. Lacagnina Undergraduate student Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in roder	2012	R. Bastle	Graduate student	DNA oligonucleotide probe radio-labeling
2010 M. Lacagnina Undergraduate student Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in roder	2011	A. Maple	Graduate student	DNA ribonucleotide probe radio-labeling
	2011	J. Huang	Graduate student	ANOVA and regression analysis
2009 W. Chu Undergraduate student Tissue sectioning with cryostat	2010	M. Lacagnina	Undergraduate student	Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in rodents
	2009	W. Chu	Undergraduate student	Tissue sectioning with cryostat

Publications and Works in Progress

A. Parga & C. Ransom. Impaired tonic current modulation after traumatic brain injury relays on GABAAδ subunit function. In preparation.

A. Parga & T. Anderson. Targeted optogenetic pyramidal neurons to regulate cortical spreading depression. In preparation.

A. Parga & T. Anderson. Neurosteroids facilitate cortical spreading depression. *Journal of Neurophysiology*. Submitted.

A. Parga, G. Muñoz & R. P. Hammer (2016) Excessive striatal dopamine activates auditory cortex via striatothalamo-cortical projections in the rat. *Biological Psychiatry* 77(9), 62S. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2015.03.006

A. N. Hoffman, **A. Parga**, P. Paode, L. R. Watterson, E. M. Nikulina, R. P. Hammer, Jr., and C. D. Conrad (2015). Chronic stress-enhanced fear memories are associated with induced amygdala zif268 expression and are resistant to reconsolidation. *Neurobiology of Learning and Memory*, 120, 61-8. http://doi: 10.1016/j.nlm.2015.02.004.

A. Parga & R. P Hammer (2012). Auditory cortical activation after dopamine infusion in caudal caudatoputamen of the rat. *Biological Psychiatry*, 71(8), 312S. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.02.014

Presentations and Awards

48th Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience – 2018

Poster: Modulation of extrasynaptic $GABA_A$ receptor function in dentate gyrus granule cells by $GABA_B$ receptors and severe TBI.

Department of Physiology and Biophysics Seminar, University of Washington – 2017

Presentation: Targeted optogenetic stimulation of cortical pyramidal neurons to regulate cortical spreading depression

 46^{th} Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience – 2016

Poster: Neurosteroids selectively disinhibit the cortex and facilitate cortical spreading depression

45th Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience – 2015

Poster: Cortical spreading depression induced by targeted optogenetic activation of cortical pyramidal neurons

70th Annual Scientific Convention of the Society of Biological Psychiatry – 2015

Presentation: Excessive striatal dopamine activates auditory cortex via striato-thalamo-cortical projections in the rat

Arizona State University Graduate College Dissertation Fellowship - 2013

Award: Cortical auditory functional activation by cortico-striato-thalamo-cortico circuits: How excessive dopaminergic transmission in the caudatoputamen activates sound-like cortical patterns.

43rd Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience - 2013

Trans-synaptic retrograde tracing of an auditory cortico-striato-thalamic-cortico circuit with PRV-152

68th Annual Scientific Convention of the Society of Biological Psychiatry – 2013

Presentation: Attenuation of striatal dopamine-induced auditory cortical activation by D1 or D2 receptor-selective antagonist in the rat

Nominated for best poster presentation

4th BNI-ASU Research Symposium - 2012

Poster: Sound-like functional pattern of auditory activation induced by dopamine in caudal caudatoputamen

67th Annual Scientific Convention of the Society of Biological Psychiatry - 2012

Poster: Auditory Cortical Activation after Dopamine Infusion in Caudal Caudatoputamen of the Rat

41st Annual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience - 2011

Poster: Effects of repeated PCP and chronic clozapine treatment on the 5-choice serial reaction time task and regional brain zif268 expression

Medical Experience

Emergency Physician

La Arandia Military Base (supported by the United States), National Army of Colombia 08/2005 – 05/2006

Emergency Medical Services

- Provided medical emergency care for privates of anti-narcotics battalions I, II, and III, including helicopter supported evacuations and emergency transfers
- Attended to in/out patients and developed and maintained clinical records for a billeted population of 1500 soldiers (both Colombian and American)
- Physician in charge of the Military Base's Medical Health Center coordinating surgical medical brigades and the emergency personnel, including 16 registered nurses

Hospital Management and Training Activities

- Organized pharmacy budget and ordered pharmacy supplies for La Arandia Military Base's dispensary according to epidemiological data
- Trained nurses in first aid care and resuscitation protocols according to the American Heart Association's (AHA) Advanced Cardiovascular Life Support course (ACLS)

Tropical Diseases Services

- Supervised Leishmaniasis and Malaria treatment for 100+ patients
- Compiled, coded, and reported epidemiologic and demographic data to the Ministry of Health according to morbidity and mortality statistics

Postgraduate Medical Training

12/2012 Advanced cardiovascular life support provider (ACLS program)
American Heart Association, Safety On Site Training, Phoenix

Emergency Physician (Clerkship)

07/2004 – 10/2004 Gyneco-Obstetric Services, San Rafael Hospital, Colombia

• Provided medical care in obstetrics emergencies, birth assistance and neonatal adaptations for 25+ obstetric emergency visits per shift

10/2004 – 05/2005 Emergency, Surgery, Internal Medicine and Pediatric Services, Ramon Gonzalez Valencia Hospital, Colombia

- Maintained patients' clinical records. Examined and reported on anamneses and physical examinations
- Interpreted and reported on laboratory assessments to chief medical specialists. Ordered, collected and verified medical orders for chief medical staff
- Assisted appointments of specialized medical cases. In charge of patients' follow up throughout surgical and post-surgical procedures

05/2005 – 08/2005 Psychiatric Services, San Camilo Hospital, Colombia

- Researched and proposed treatment alternatives for medical cases at the emergency department for 10+ psychiatric emergencies per shift
- Documented and reported literature reviews on psychiatric conditions to chief medical specialists

Skills

Research procedures: Transynaptic retrograde tracing of neuronal circuits using pseudorabies virus, in vitro and in vivo electrophysiology recordings of neurons, Intrisic Optical Signal imaging, Stereotaxic intracranial surgeries in rodents, fluorogold iontophoretc infusions, *in situ* hybridization histochemistry, immunohistochemistry, Confocal and Multifocal microscopy

Medical procedures: Cesarean section, labor assistance and neonatal adaptation, thoracic chest tube insertion, upper and lower extremity block, skin closure, surgical debridement, spinal tap

Analytic Software: Python, PolyScan2, Axon Imaging Workbench, Clampex, Stereoinvestigator, Neurolucida, SPSS, SAS, STATA, Blackboard 9, Canvas, LabScribe, Biopac, Blaise, CDISC

Languages

English – native proficiency Spanish – native proficiency